Daniel Carroll of Duddington Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Daniel Carroll Papers 1662-1920 (bulk 1791-1868)
MSS15206
Carroll, Daniel, 1764-1849
3,100 items
10 containers plus 1 oversize
4.4 linear feet
8 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Landowner and businessman. Correspondence, financial and legal records, plat surveys, and newspaper clippings pertaining to Carroll's business interests and real estate holdings in Washington, D.C., and Baltimore, Md.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Appleby, George F.--Correspondence.; Brent, Richard, 1757-1814--Correspondence.; Brent, William Leigh, 1784-1848--Correspondence.; Carroll family.; Carroll, Ann C.; Carroll, Ann C.--Correspondence.; Carroll, Charles, -1820--Correspondence.; Carroll, Charles, 1737-1832--Correspondence.; Carroll, Daniel, 1730-1796--Correspondence.; Carroll, Daniel, 1764-1849.; Clarke, Richard H. (Richard Henry), 1827-1911--Correspondence.; Emory, Thomas, 1782- --Correspondence.; Fitzhugh, Maria Carroll.; Gittings, John Sterrett--Correspondence.; Gordon, William Alexander, -1873--Correspondence.; Greenleaf, James, 1765-1843--Correspondence.; Hammond, William A. (William Alexander), 1828-1900--Correspondence.; Hickey, William, 1798-1866--Correspondence.; Johnson, Christopher, active 19th century--Correspondence.; L'Enfant, Pierre Charles, 1754-1825.; McPherson, James Birdseye, 1828-1864--Correspondence.; Merryman, John, 1824-1881--Correspondence.; Waggaman, Thos. E. (Thomas E.)--Correspondence.
Organizations
Baltimore Iron Works (Baltimore, Md.); Duddington Manor (Washington, D.C.); Hockley Forge.
Subjects
Iron industry and trade--Maryland.; Real property--Maryland--Baltimore.; Real property--Washington (D.C.); Rent.
Places
Baltimore (Md.)--Surveys.; Capitol Hill (Washington, D.C.); Washington (D.C.)--History.; Washington (D.C.)--Surveys.
Occupations
Businessmen.; Landowners.
Provenance
The papers of Daniel Carroll, landowner and businessman, were deposited and then given to the Library of Congress in 1963 and 1967 by Mrs. Harry G. Meem and her daughter, Ann Meem Rogers, descendants of the Carroll family. Other gifts and purchases were received between 1920 and 1990, including gifts from Frank Hannegan in 1983 and 1985.
Additional Guides
Portions of the collection are described in the Quarterly Journal of the Library of Congress, vol. 21, July 1964, pp. 191-194, and in Library of Congress Acquisitions: Manuscript Division, 1983, pp. 6-10.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Daniel Carroll are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on eight reels from the Library's Photoduplication Service for purchase subject to the Copyright Law of the United States (Title 17, U.S.C.). Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Daniel Carroll of Duddington (1764-1849) span the years 1662-1920, with the bulk of the material concentrated between 1791 and 1868. The collection relates principally to the real estate and business interests of Carroll, an influential Washington, D.C., landowner whose property included Duddington Manor on the Anacostia River and much of what was to become Capitol Hill. The papers are organized in the following series: Family Correspondence, General Correspondence, Financial Records, Miscellany, an Addition, and Oversize.
The collection deals with the surveying and selling of lots and squares in the new federal city and in Baltimore, Maryland, with lawsuits and the collection of rents, and with Carroll's large holdings in the Baltimore Iron Works and the Hockley Forge. Most of the material dated after Carroll's death in 1849 concerns the settlement of his estate by his daughters, Ann C. Carroll and Maria Carroll Fitzhugh.
Principal correspondents from Daniel Carroll's lifetime include his uncle, Daniel Carroll of Rock Creek, one of the early commissioners of the District of Columbia; Charles Carroll (d. 1820) of Belle Vue; and Charles Carroll (1737-1832) of Carrollton, a signer of the Declaration of Independence. Other correspondents are Richard Brent, William Leigh Brent, Thomas Emory, James Greenleaf, William Alexander Hammond, Christopher Johnson, and John Merryman. Correspondents from the period after Carroll's death include George Appleby, Ann C. Carroll, Richard H. Clarke, John Sterrett Gittings, William Alexander Gordon, William Hickey, James Birseye McPherson, and Thos. E. Waggaman.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Family Correspondence, 1758-1830
General Correspondence, 1662-1910
Financial Records, 1752-1906
Miscellany, 1702-1920
Addition, 1820
Oversize, 1702-1872
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 19,756
- Family Correspondence, 1758-1830 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  Correspondence of various family members.
  Arranged by name of family member and thereunder chronologically.
  - Carroll, Charles, of Belle Vue, 1792-1822, undated (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Carroll, Charles, of Duddington, and his wife, Mary Hill Carroll, letterbook, 1758-1774 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Carroll, Charles, of Carrollton, 1772-1819, undated (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - Miscellaneous family members, 1786-1833, undated (Box 1, Reel 1)
- General Correspondence, 1662-1910 (Box 1-6, Reel 1-4)
  Letters received and some letters sent.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1662-1795, (7 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 1796-1814, (11 folders) (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
  - 1815-1827, (13 folders) (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - 1828-1846, (12 folders) (Box 4, Reel 2-3)
  - 1847-1868, (15 folders) (Box 5, Reel 3-4)
  - 1869-1910, undated, (11 folders) (Box 6, Reel 4)
- Financial Records, 1752-1906 (Box 7-8, Reel 5-7)
  Family business records including accounts, receipts, correspondence, and related material.
  - 1752-1840, (13 folders) (Box 7, Reel 5)
  - 1841-1906, undated, (9 folders) (Box 8, Reel 6-7)
- Miscellany, 1702-1920 (Box 9-10, Reel 7-8)
  Autograph albums, business records, clippings and pamphlets, land plats, land reference books, lottery tickets, miscellaneous notations, indentures, wills, photograph, report, subpoenas, verses, and annotated wrappers.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Autograph albums, 1860-1873, (2 folders) (Box 9, Reel 7-8)
  - Business records, 1749-1822 (Box 9, Reel 7-8)
  - Clippings and pamphlets, 1804-1906, undated (Box 9, Reel 7-8)
  - Land plats, 1793-1874, undated (Box 9, Reel 7-8)
  - Land reference books, notebooks, 1853, undated (Box 9, Reel 7-8)
  - Lottery tickets, undated (Box 9, Reel 7-8)
  - Miscellaneous notations, 1796, 1850s-1860s, (3 folders) (Box 9, Reel 7-8)
  - Oversize material See Oversize series (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - Photograph, undated (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - Recipe book, undated (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - Report on construction of canal, by Benjamin Henry Latrobe, Feb. 5, 1804 (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - Scrapbook, 1793-1920 (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - Subpoenas, Merrick v. Fitzhugh, 1868-1872 (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - "Verses," by A. G. Heaton, Sept. 23, 1885 (Box 10, Reel 8)
  - Wrappers, annotated, undated, (3 folders) (Box 10, Reel 8)
- Addition, 1820 (Box 10)
  Photocopies of a letter and an essay pertaining to signers of the Declaration of Independence.
  Arranged by type of material.
  - Letter (photocopy), Charles Carroll of Belle Vue to his sister, 1820 (Box 10)
  - Essay (photocopy) by Charles Carroll of Belle Vue pertaining to the signers of the Declaration of Independence, undated (Box 10)
- Oversize, 1702-1872 (Box OV 1, Reel 8)
  Atlas, indentures, land plats, correspondence, insurance policy, and wills. Microfilmed as part of Miscellany series.
  Arranged and described according to the series, container, and folder from which the items were removed.
  - Atlas, undated (Container 10) (Box OV 1, Reel 8)
  - Correspondence, 1760 (Container 10) (Box OV 1, Reel 8)
  - Indentures, 1702-1800 (Container 10) (Box OV 1, Reel 8)
  - Land plats, 1796-1872 (Container 10) (Box OV 1, Reel 8)
  - Insurance policy, 1803 (Container 10) (Box OV 1, Reel 8)
  - Wills, 1734-1828 (Container 10) (Box OV 1, Reel 8)